how would you define holistic science
and the main what what the main point is
that you try to communicate to your
students and main learning experience
well the the components of the Masters
and mystics hands well one way of
looking after the many ways of asking
that question isn't one answer basically
but one answer one once it might be that
it's to do with an approach to the world
that is not just about thinking but the
name incorporates thinking into
intuition our sensory experience and our
an ethical response to the world
or if you put differently it's a kind of
science where you recognizes that ethics
is built into the very structure of
nature and it's not as if nature is it's
dead mechanical backdrop that we thought
it was up until the beginning of the
20th century in science so it's actually
it has an ethics deep within it which
can communicate itself to us in other
words that nature is actually sentient
and that we are able to learn and
participate with this sentence in nature
through our thinking amounts through our
intellects which we mustn't reject but
just as much and just as importantly
through our ethics our feeling that is
through our sensory experience and
through our intuition so it's a
combination list excite is a combination
of using those four ways of million
ourselves in developing and participate
or relationship with the world and you
in in your recent book the animal earth
and you try the scientific information
of Gaia theory in with aspects of Deep
Ecology and also of Jungian psychology
could you and say a little bit about
that yeah how you see them connect mmm
well it's again using that fourfold
model which I outlined just now which
comes from you thinking feeling sensing
and intuition and in science we just use
thinking convened
science we just use thinking and that's
it the others are more or less
disregarded or their faintly
acknowledged if at all but in that book
what I try to do is take the scientific
information and real and solid literally
reanimated brings soul back in to the
scientific descriptions of violent
cycles such as the carbon cycle or the
sulfur cycle by speaking of the actors
in the feedback loops as personalities
not not as if they were personalities
but actually as persons in some broader
sense of what we mean by person as
sentient creatures that are capable of
experience so carbon atoms have a
personality oxygen atoms have
personalities the great ecosystems have
personality their qualities so I try to
describe some of the standard scientific
accounts of guy and fleabag loose from
that perspective in where do you see the
enrichment and in when you when you
speak about nature in that way well what
does it do to people and to people's
understanding well is it it can develop
a very strong sense of participation and
it's realistic in the sense that it
doesn't reject any way of knowing I mean
the tendency either is either to could
stay with irrational completely and
reject the others this gives you a
partial understanding or to go with
feeling or intuition or sensing and
reject the intellect which gives you
another partial understanding what we're
trying to do here is bring those two
sides together the quantities and the
qualities the facts and the values the
culture and nature these dichotomies we
have created in our culture since the
Scientific Revolution to bring them
together and I find that when we work
like this with students who are studying
Gaia or science generally a tremendous
sense of participation in the world can
happen in fact one way I put it is that
students or people can be guided by the
very personality of the earth so it's
not as if as if the earth is alive not
as if the earth in this this understand
she is alive and actually is a
psychological presence actually does
have a soul and this unsold quality of
the earth is agents in the earth can
sweep through your consciousness and
open it up and broaden it out and
inspire it and embed you deeply within
itself and I think this is what we need
to discover if we're going to move
towards genuine sustainability otherwise
our efforts to become sustainable won't
work because they'll be founded on the
wrong perspective and of course this
perspective around talking about is
nothing new it goes way back into the
roots of our own culture and we see it
in I think I could say or tribal
additional traditional indigenous
cultures this notion of the earth or
home of nature is an animal being is
really a primordial way of seeing the
world which I think we in our company to
rediscover and we are part of that being
completely behind it you know so how
does our psychology relate to they've
also been quite strongly influenced by
Anna Nessun and the deep ecologist and
where do you see the link to to your
work now from that influence and mmm
well Deep Ecology I think is about
experience fundamentally about a deep
experience of the centres of the world
because how I would put it is not how I
mean s to put it but it's how it is the
ecology is about a deep experience of
the center of nature of the world so
honey nests would say things like I'm
not going to the mountains I'm going to
be with the mountains so he would go to
his mountain hut and in Norway and just
be with the mountains by that he means
he would speak absorb the wisdom of the
mountain singers be taught by the
mountains this is a deep experience of
deep connectedness and then in deep
ecology we go further than that we then
say okay how can we live our lives in
accordance with that deep experience and
then the more rational aspect comes in
and we begin to deeply question our
lifestyles in
relation to that deep experience and
then we act having deeply questioned how
we're living with an act and it becomes
a kind of hermeneutic circle these three
things are connected with each other and
you get a increasing depth of experience
of questioning and commitment and so the
work with an ammeter that I was doing in
that book is really trying to use the
science to drive that depth and that
deepening and